It is said that sheep were the first to enter the orifices.
最先進入洞裡的生物據說是一頭綿羊
But the first human to enter is said to be a live streamer.
至於最先進入洞裡的人類 聽說是一名男性直播主
The man claimed to be an illustrator,
該男自稱是一名插畫師
but since he only had work every six months,
但他半年只接得到一個案子
he wanted to gain recognition.
因此渴望獲取知名度
Today, I am going to explore this orifice to see what it is and where it leads,
今天我要進洞探索 看裡面到底有什麼，究竟通往哪裡
so I brought all the food I need.
我還帶了充足的糧食
It could get dangerous if I encounter monsters along the way.
另外，為了避免中途碰上什麼怪物 感覺到時候會很危險
That's why I also packed some garlic and a cross to fight them off.
我還帶了大蒜和十字架 會用它們來擊退怪物
-ISN'T IT DANGEROUS? -SO EXCITING!
（感覺很危險吧？ 讓人興奮！）
It's pretty dark in here. Can you guys see me?
裡面幾乎完全無光 你們看得到我的臉嗎？
You can? Okay, good.
看得到？那就好
The temperature?
氣溫嗎？
It's not exactly cold but it's chilly.
不會很冷，就是涼涼的
Hold on, I brought a device to measure the temperature.
對了，我有帶溫度計 現在就拿出來測測看
And humidity too.
這還能測濕度喔
By the way, I haven't sensed anything unusual so far.
順帶一提，目前沒感覺到 有其他東西存在
Huh?
奇怪
I've been walking straight, haven't I?
我明明一路都直線前進，對吧？
I haven't walked that much. Maybe like three minutes, right?
應該也沒走多久才對 頂多三分多鐘吧？
What?! No reception?
怎麼會？沒訊號了
Here it is.
就是這個
Oh, this is it…
好，這就是…
It's not very detailed, though.
內容統整得意外地簡略
There's a list of those who entered and those who haven't.
是用“最後有沒有進去”來分類
Does it mention why some didn't enter?
有沒有記錄“沒進去的理由”？
Briefly.
只有簡單帶過
Yes, it's vague.
對，這本書就是寫得很簡略
It's very helpful, though.
但還是滿有參考價值的
-Thank you. -Sure.
-謝謝你 -不客氣
It has notes from previous people and might come in handy.
這裡還有之前的人 留下的筆記，所以沒問題
It's almost like a history book.
好像歷史書喔
Don't you all have this in your rooms?
你們的房間裡應該也都有吧？
My room only had magazines of barbecue and camping.
我房間裡只有烤肉和露營主題的雜誌
And a scented candle the previous person left.
還有香氛蠟燭 大概是前一個人留下的
That's nice. I want to light a scented candle too.
香氛蠟燭很讚耶，我會想拿來點
-Do you want me to bring it? -Tonight.
-要我去拿過來嗎？ -等晚上吧
Okay, tonight.
好，晚上再說
Who's entering the orifices next?
接下來還有誰會比較早進去？
I'm going on the 21st.
我21號
I'm scheduled for the 13th.
我13號會進去
-Thirteenth? -I'm on the 8th.
-13號？ -我是8號
Anyone else going before that?
還有更早的人嗎？
Are we going to do this every time? Let's just write it down.
我們要每次都要重問一遍嗎？ 把順序記錄下來吧
Can you write it down, then?
那就麻煩你了
What, me?
等等，我來寫？
You're the one who suggested it.
是你說要寫的啊
I'll do it.
我來寫吧
Thank you.
謝謝
So, my story begins with first love.
這要從我的初戀開始說起
I used to do karate.
我以前有練過空手道
I believe I was in third grade of elementary school.
大概是從小學三年級開始
That's when I started karate.
就一直有在練
Now, I've lost all my muscle.
現在肌肉都退化了啦
I started because my father liked martial arts.
當初開始練的契機是我爸 他喜歡格鬥技
He wanted me to try it.
就想讓我練
I wasn't really keen on it at first.
但我不太想練就是了
In third grade, I tried out a karate class and started attending that dojo.
小學三年級時我去了道場參加體驗課 最後決定正式去那裡上課
My classes are tough. Will you be able to keep up?
正式課程會比體驗課 更辛苦喔，你受得了嗎？
Thank you for accepting him.
麻煩老師了
Can you do it?
你能努力嗎？
Answer me.
回答我啊
Uh-huh.
嗯
You also didn't greet when you entered the dojo.
你進道場時也沒問候吧
You have to greet when you enter. Got it?
以後進門的時候要記得問候一聲
Okay.
好
Let me hear your voices.
喊出聲音來
-Osu!
-是！
Fore fist punch stance.
預備打出正拳
One.
一
Two.
二
Three.
三
Four.
四
Five.
五
Louder!
大聲點！
-Osu!
-是！
Six.
六
Seven.
七
Eight.
八
Raise your voices!
聲音要喊出來！
-Osu!
-是！
The response is osu.
聽到要回“是”
Don't look at your mother!
不要看你媽！
Response?
回答呢？
Yes.
好的
It's osu!
要講“是”！
O-Osu.
是…
Nine.
九
Ten.
十
Eleven.
十一
That's the kind of dojo I was attending.
這就是我當年去的道場
Apparently, he doesn't smack his students anymore.
聽說現在已經不會打學生屁股了
But he was a very strict sensei.
不過這位老師是真的很嚴格
Every year, this dojo had a three-day training camp.
這個道場每年 會辦一次三天兩夜的集訓
We ate meals the sensei cooked, bathed together at a public bathhouse,
這期間三餐都吃老師做的飯菜 所有學員一起在附近的澡堂洗澡
and slept in the training hall.
晚上就在道館過夜
That kind of training camp.
就是這樣的集訓活動
The first time I attended that camp…
而我第一次參加集訓時…
Huh?
什麼？
I'm cold. Can I sleep with you?
好冷喔，讓我進去
Oh…
哦
Okay.
好吧
The bathroom was freezing.
廁所超冷的
Oh, yeah?
是喔
Did you go?
你去過廁所了嗎？
No, I didn't.
還沒耶
It's super creepy.
超恐怖的
Oh, yeah?
這樣啊
I don't want to have my back facing the bathroom, so can I lean against you?
背對廁所我會怕，可以背對你嗎？
Okay.
可以啊
Don't you find it creepy sleeping near the bathroom?
你睡得離廁所最近，都不會怕喔？
I don't believe in ghosts at all.
我根本就不相信世界上有鬼
She snuck into my futon again the next night.
隔天她再次鑽進我的被窩
That's when I started being attracted to her.
於是我就開始在意她了
But I was just a kid in elementary school and didn't know what to do.
但當時我還是個小學生 根本不知道該怎麼辦
Moreover, all students of this dojo went to different schools,
而且這個道場的學員 來自很多不同的學校
so I only knew her name.
除了名字，我對她一無所知
Thinking back, Sugaya vaguely remembers
菅谷回想當年那場集訓
holding hands for the first time while sleeping during this camp.
他似乎在睡夢中第一次跟女孩子牽手
However, after all these years, his memory is fuzzy.
但如今長大成人，回憶早已模糊 他無法確定那究竟是不是事實
Although I couldn't even ask for her phone number during the camp,
即使我連她的聯絡方式都沒要到
I consider that my first love.
我仍認為這三天兩夜就是我的初戀
Her name was Ms. Mori.
不過我和那位女孩，毛利同學
But since that camp, I didn't see her at the dojo anymore.
在集訓結束後 就再也沒在道場碰過面
Are karate classes only on Tuesdays?
空手道只有星期二有開課嗎？
They also have children's classes on Wednesdays and Fridays.
週三跟週五也有小學生空手道班喔
Can I switch to another day?
那我可以換一天去嗎？
Why?
為什麼要換？
Because…
沒有啦
On Tuesdays, I also have PE before my karate lesson,
只是因為星期二有體育課
so it's exhausting.
放學後接著練空手道有點累
You also have PE on Fridays.
星期五也有體育課啊
But it's in the second period.
星期五的體育在第二節課
First, I switched to Fridays, where I had PE in the second period.
因為週五的體育課在第二節 我先把空手道班的時間換到了那天
If she didn't come, I would then change to Wednesdays, where I didn't have PE.
要是沒看到她，我想再跟媽媽說 想改成沒有體育課的週三去
However, even after switching days, Sugaya did not see her again.
然而即使改了上課日期 菅谷仍然沒能見到她
After about a year, I quit karate.
大約一年後，我就放棄空手道了
I started playing basketball and played on my junior high school team.
開始打籃球 待在籃球社直到國中畢業
My first relationship was in my third year.
國三時我交了第一任女友
We were together for three months.
在一起三個月左右
But I didn't want my friends to find out,
但我不想被別人知道我交女友
so I broke up with her before they found out.
所以就趁事情曝光前先分手
I did have my fair share of girlfriends.
後來我交往過的對象絕對不算少
I never thought about Ms. Mori again.
但我從來不曾回想起毛利同學的事
Sugaya coincidentally met Mori again in his second year of university.
菅谷與毛利的偶然重逢 發生在他剛升上大二時
It happened while he was running an errand for his host family in the US.
當時他住在美國的寄宿家庭 受託去超市採買
Is your host family making you run errands?
你被派來跑腿喔？
How did you know?
被你看出來了？
My host mother told me to go buy my own food.
還不是寄宿家庭的媽媽 叫我來買自己要吃的量
You should tell the school.
去跟學校反應一下吧
It's because I eat a lot and she doesn't know how much to buy.
只是因為我吃太多 她不知道要準備多少食材
There's an all-you-can-eat party in two days. Do you want to come?
後天倒是有一場派對 可以讓你盡情吃到飽，你去不去？
Where at?
地點在哪？
-The whiskey's over there. -Okay.
-那邊有威士忌 -好
You want anything? They only have whiskey, though.
要幫你加點什麼嗎？ 雖然這裡也只有威士忌就是了
I'll have that, then.
那就給我吧
Why do they only have whiskey?
這裡真的只有威士忌嗎？
I was told we could have whatever's in the fridge.
他們說冰箱裡的飲料也可以自由取用
Cool.
真棒
First time here?
你是第一次來？
My friend Masaya invited me.
是我的朋友雅也邀我來的
-I don't know anyone else. -Studying abroad?
-其他人我都不認識 -你來留學？
-Yes, I'm staying with a host family. -Second year?
-對，住在寄宿家庭 -今年大二嗎？
Am I that obvious?
你怎麼什麼都知道？
Starting to crave Japanese friends, huh?
我現在正好處在 渴望結交日本人朋友的時期
It seems like I don't even need to talk.
但你都不透露自己的事
One more thing. You're from Tokyo.
讓我再猜一件事 你來自東京對不對？
You've nailed it.
全都被你猜中了
My turn.
那接下來換我
Are you here by yourself?
你是一個人來的嗎？
No, with friends.
沒有，我跟朋友一起來的
You're bad at this.
你倒是完全猜錯了呢
I kind of thought we went to the same school.
就覺得我們應該是同一所學校的
You smoke?
你會抽菸啊？
I just started.
最近開始嘗試的
I used to play sports, so I didn't like cigarettes.
因為從以前開始 我就有在運動，才不喜歡菸
What kind of sports?
像是什麼運動？
This and that.
很多啊
I played basketball in junior high school,
有練過籃球，但只打到國中畢業
and then softball in high school.
高中有打過壘球之類的
I quit, though.
不過後來也沒練了
In elementary school, I did karate.
小學的時候練過格鬥技，空手道
I see.
是喔
I used to do karate too.
我以前也學過空手道
Full contact? What style?
是真的會對人拳打腳踢的那種？ 什麼流派的？
I did karate until my third year of junior high.
我一直練到國三
At Mr. Ushigome's dojo.
在牛込老師的門下
Wait, Mr. Ushigome?
等等，牛込老師？
The Mr. Ushigome?
你是說牛込老師？
He's a famous martial artist, so you might have heard of him.
他好像是一位滿有名的武術家 你可能有聽說過
I know him all too well.
何止是聽說過
I asked her if she remembered the camp.
我立刻就反問她記不記得集訓的事
Of course I remember.
我當然記得啊
I was scared of the bathroom.
那個廁所真的很恐怖嘛
Since then, I started talking to Ms. Mori when we ran into each other at school.
從那之後我們的交流就多了起來 在學校裡巧遇時就會聊天
We went out with a few people and smoked together at the smoking area.
會和其他朋友一起相約出遊 也會一起在吸菸區抽菸
I quit smoking pretty quickly, though.
雖然沒多久我就戒菸了
Hey.
嗨
If you come here so often, why not smoke?
你一天到晚都跑來，何不一起抽？
Nah, I quit already.
不用，我已經戒了
You're quick to give up.
你太快做決定了
I got fed up of smoking.
我就是覺得不需要再抽了
I'm hoping to find work here in the US.
我考慮留在美國就業
That's impressive.
真了不起
Have you found anything yet?
已經找好去處了嗎？
Uh-huh.
對
I might look for work here too.
乾脆我也在這工作好了
Do you know what you want to do?
你有想做的事嗎？
Hm…
這個嘛…
This might be the first time I let someone into my place.
其實我好像是第一次找人來這個住處
Sugaya's homestay period was coming to an end,
由於期限已到 菅谷必須離開寄宿家庭
and he was scheduled to fly back to Japan the next day.
預計隔天就要回國
A farewell dinner on Christmas Eve, huh?
在平安夜幫你開個送別會
What will you do back in Japan?
回國後有什麼打算？
I'm going to eat a ton of Japanese food.
我要狂吃日本的料理
I totally get that.
我懂你的心情
No matter how long I live here, I will always crave Japanese food.
相信不管在這裡待多少年 我的那種渴望永遠都不會消失
Want some?
要來一根嗎？
No, I'm good.
不用啦
I got them for you because you're leaving.
這可是我特別為你準備的餞別禮耶
Oh?
什麼？
Huh?
怪了
W-What?
搞什麼？
Wait…
是怎樣？
Is something going on?
這真的沒問題嗎？
You're spinning.
在旋轉耶
Me?
我嗎？
What?
怎麼回事？
What's going on?
這樣真的沒問題嗎？
I'm going to fly. I'm going to fly away.
我會飛起來，會被甩飛喔
-The centrifugal force is insane. -What?
離心力太強了
You're not spinning.
我們才沒有在旋轉呢
It's not spinning
沒在轉啊
Wait a minute, hey!
等等，嘿！
-We definitely are spinning. -No, we're not.
-我們明明就有在轉… -不，才沒有呢
We're not spinning.
我們沒有在轉啦，你想多了
Oh my gosh.
我的天啊
Whoa…
轉得好快…
We are spinning.
真的有在轉嘛
No, we're not spinning.
沒有啦，哪有在轉
We're not.
真的沒有啦
Sugaya returned to Japan and started working.
菅谷回國後，在日本就業
The next time he encountered Mori was
後來與毛利再次重逢已是八年後
I got off the plane and ran to the bathroom.
當時我一下飛機就立刻衝去廁所
I was in such a hurry that I didn't check the restroom signs.
因為實在是太急了 沒看清楚自己進的是男廁還是女廁
But while I was in the restroom, I suddenly felt anxious.
廁所上到一半我才突然開始擔心
I sat with my feet up so they weren't visible from under the door.
還特地把腳抬高 避免別人從底下的門縫看到我的腿毛
When I came out and was washing my hands…
後來就在我走出去洗手的時候…
O-Oh?
不會吧？
That's a reasonable reaction.
這是合理的反應吧
We hadn't met in eight years
我們是時隔八年久違重逢
and what are the chances of meeting at an airport in Egypt?
重逢的地方竟然還是埃及的機場 實在是巧過頭了
On top of that, I had accidentally entered the women's restrooms.
而且還是因為我誤闖女廁才碰到面
That too but…
是沒錯啦…
Wait, let's get out of here first.
等等，我們先出去吧
I took her hand,
說完我就牽起她的手
pulled her out of the restrooms and realized…
出了廁所外我才發現
She was wearing a ring.
她手上戴著戒指
Ms. Mori was on vacation with her fiancé.
毛利小姐是和未婚夫一起來旅遊
I could see her fiancé waiting for her, so we didn't talk much.
遠處就站著看起來像是她未婚夫的人 所以我們也只是隨便聊了幾句
But we did exchange our phone numbers.
但也不知道是誰先提的 我們倒是有交換聯絡方式
You wish to get married?
你想結婚嗎？
I do.
想啊
We never contacted each other.
後來我們都沒有聯絡對方
The third encounter was a year later.
一年後，我們第三次重逢
She contacted me that she had moved back to Japan.
毛利小姐主動聯絡了我 說她搬回了日本
I didn't expect to meet you again in this way.
我沒想到會跟你這樣再會
After all, we didn't stay in touch.
畢竟我們也沒聯絡對方
You could've reached out to me.
都交換聯絡方式了 幹嘛不聯絡一下啊？
I did.
我這不是做了嗎？
Took you long enough.
你害我等很久
Well, you didn't reach out either.
你還不是一樣，沒資格說我吧
Speaking of…
說到這個
I was wondering when you'd start working in the US.
我之前一直在期待 你什麼時候要來美國工作
Me?
什麼？我嗎？
I kept wondering what kind of company you wanted to work for.
我一直都很好奇你會進什麼公司工作
I don't know.
我也不知道耶
It was more of a joke, really.
不過我那時候其實只是在開玩笑啦
That's what I thought.
果然是玩笑啊
Where do you live?
你現在住在哪裡？
In Shimouma.
下馬那邊
We're heading in the same direction then.
那我們同個方向耶
When we were in the States, I thought you were hot.
當年還待在美國的時候 其實我覺得你還滿帥的
Duh.
我懂
Not anymore, though.
現在可就不這麼想囉
My friends were sure you wouldn't come back and told me not to wait for you.
但那時我朋友卻跟我說 你絕對不會在美國工作，叫我別等了
Sorry, I didn't mean it like that
抱歉，我當時說想工作
when I said I wanted to get a job in the US.
完全沒有那種意思
I know.
我知道
Um…
別誤會
It's not that I didn't like you or didn't have feelings for you.
也不是說我沒把你當成戀愛對象 或我不喜歡你
So, yeah.
所以說啊
I liked you.
我算是喜歡你
I see.
這樣啊
It's just not what "getting a job" meant.
唯獨工作那件事，我不是那個意思
I broke up with my fiancée the other day.
我前陣子和未婚妻分手了
How long were you together?
你們何時開始交往的？
When we met in Egypt, I was already engaged to her.
其實我們在埃及巧遇時 我也已經跟別人訂婚了
I see.
是喔
I got married last month.
我跟丈夫上個月登記結婚了
Oh?
哦？
I see.
這樣啊
I'm getting off here.
只有一個人要下車
-See you. -Yup.
-再見囉 -好
I kind of felt I would never see her again.
當時我隱約覺得 我們應該不會再見面了
I think…
我在猜啊
it was a lie that she'd gotten married.
她說跟丈夫登記了，應該是騙人的
I think she'd broken up with her fiancé.
那時候毛利小姐 應該已經跟未婚夫分手了
But I'd lied to her too.
但其實我也騙了她
I think we both knew we were lying.
我和她大概都有意識到對方在說謊
I was engaged to my current wife,
當時我已經和現在的太太訂婚了
and we were living together.
甚至還已經同居了
Who did you like more?
你比較喜歡哪一個？
That's a harsh question.
這個問題也太不留情了吧
Well…
這個嘛
I reached out to Ms. Mori once, but she didn't reply.
後來我有聯絡過她一次，但她沒回
There's your answer.
那看來答案很明顯了
Your poor wife.
真是可憐啊
I might lose hope in marriage if I can't be with my true love.
如果不能跟真心喜歡的人在一起 我大概會對婚姻失望
Don't get me wrong, I love my wife.
我們夫妻的婚姻生活還是很恩愛啦
From your story, it's hard to believe that.
聽完你剛才說的故事 誰還相信你這句話啊
No, I mean it.
不，是真的啦
I don't know, though…
不過或許我後來遭天譴了
Maybe it's karma.
或者說現世報吧
My wife and I were blessed with a child,
我們曾經有過一個孩子
but the doctor told us our child wouldn't live long.
然而醫生卻告訴我們那孩子活不久
Well…
不過呢
Karma doesn't sound right.
“遭天譴”這個說法聽起來滿刺耳的
But it's easier for me to think that way and punish myself.
但用那種想法來懲戒自己 反而讓我心裡比較好過
Such a tiny human being is already destined to die.
孩子還那麼小，就注定要早逝
And what's more, before me.
而且還是比我先走一步
Yet, all we can do is wait.
然而我們卻對此無能為力 只能靜靜等待那天的到來
I just can't accept the fact that everyone dies
人終有一死，這是理所當然的事
as anything other than a punishment.
但將此當成天譴才能讓我好受一點
And that's when the orifices appeared.
就在此時，洞出現了
Oh no.
不好了
Did I bring down the mood?
糟糕，我是不是讓氣氛變得很沉重？
That wasn't my intention, you know?
那不是我的本意
Seems like those who haven't entered yet are still in contact with Mr. Ozawa.
看來沒進去洞裡的人 還是有再跟小澤先生來往並見面
The only thing we know about Sugaya is
關於菅谷，目前我們只知道
that he probably didn't enter the orifices.
他應該沒有進入洞裡
There is even no record of him returning.
甚至沒有任何關於他歸來的紀錄
However, the person who recruited Sugaya to join the organization
不過邀請菅谷加入團體的人告訴小澤
told Ozawa that Sugaya's wife and child were living happily.
菅谷的妻小都還活得好好的
Sugaya's whereabouts remain unknown to everyone.
但菅谷本人從此音訊全無 無人知道他在哪
Subtitle translation by: Mariko Yasuoka-Sator
字幕翻譯：吳佳諭
I reserved tickets for today's show. My name is Yukie Hara.
我有預訂舞台劇的票，我叫原幸惠
A Yukie Hara with the same kanji came to see the show.
有一位跟你同名同姓的女生 已經來看過舞台劇了
It's hard to cross paths.
一直沒能見上一面呢
Who was I doing all this for?
我在做什麼？ 做這些到底都是為了誰？
Seven Orifices.
《驚天七洞》
But the orifices are there for us.
但是我們有洞